Guide to the International Woodworkers of America Local 3-101 Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
International Woodworkers of America Local 3-101 records
1935-1983
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
3120
International Woodworkers of America.$bLocal 3-101 (Everett, Wash.)
approximately 18 cubic feet
Records of the union's Local 3-101, Everett, Washington and records of small locals which merged with 101 in the 1950s.
AFL-CIO labor union representing mill and timber workers.
The International Woodworkers of America was founded in 1937 and chartered by the Congress of Industrial Organizations the same year. Since 1935 the Sawmill and Timber Workers had been organized by the American Federation of Labor under the leadership of the Brotherhood of Carpenters. However, the woodworkers' increasing dislike of Carpenter leadership and AFL trade union organization led to the break in 1937. From 1940 Local 101 represented workers in the Everett Weyerhaeuser mills and Eclipse Lumber Company. Unions which merged with Local 101 were other members active in the Snohomish Industrial Union Council, local coordinating arm of the CIO. Local 18 of Cannery Workers' branch of Internatinal Fishermen and Allied Workers of America, was also a member of the SIUC. Other local unions that merged with it included branches from Anacortes, Bellingham, Sedro Woolley, and Sultan, Washington. When Districts 2 and 3 of the union merged in 1953, the Everett local's disignation changed from 2-101 to 23-101; in 1959 it became Local 3-101.
The IWA was in competition with the AFL unions for representation of woodworkers until the AFL-CIO merger in 1955. After the industry-wide shift to the IWA, the AFL locals made gains in Everett, but the big Weyerhaeuser mills had not signed a contract with either union until 1940. In that year during the AFL strike the IWA capitalized on increasing discontent with the Brotherhood of Carpenter's leadership to organize the Weyerhaeuser mills. On October 31, 1940 the IWA signed contracts covering those mills and, in effect, pulled far ahead of the Sawmill and Timber Workers in Everett. Besides the Weyerhaeuser Mills, Local 101 also represented the Eclipse Lumber Company and, after 1953, a new Kraft mill. Since its membership was mostly in the large mills, it had greater stability than other locals. Representing Weyerhaeuser employees enhanced its position since other companies followed Weyerhaeuser's example.
Local 101 was a member of the Snohomish County Industrial Union Council (CIO), which also included the Sultan IWA local and Everett locals of the ILWU, IBU, Cannery Workers and United Construction Workers. Certain issues are common to the Local 101 records and the SIUC subgroup, such as support for the formation of a third party in 1948, support for left wing labor leaders, and repeal of the Taft-Hartley law.
Organized into 2 accessions.
Accession No. 3120-001, International Woodworkers of America Local 3-101 records, 1935-1979
Accession No. 3120-002, International Woodworkers of America Local 3-101 records, 1940-1983
This collection documents the activities of the International Woodworker’s Association (IWA) Local 3-101 (Everett). Included are series detailing the Union’s Organization, General Correspondence, Minutes of its general and executive boards, Negotiations, Strikes, Elections, Financial Activities, Wage Scales, member Grievances, and a series of publications that detail the state of the lumber industry. Activities of IWA branches that were either part of local 3-101 or merged with it at some point are represented in several records subgroup and series within the collection. These are the records of Local 23-93 (Sultan), 23-46 (Bellingham), 3-199 (Bellingham), 23-75 (Sedro Woolley), 2-54 (Anacortes), the Snohomish County Industrial Union Council, Fishermen and Allied Workers of America, International Cannery Workers. Local 18 (Everett), the Publishers Forest Products Company (Anacortes), and the Weyerhauser Standing Committee.
The records of ACCESSION NO. 3120-001 date primarily from the 1940s and 1950s. A commonly articulated concern from this period was anti-labor legislation, especially the Taft-Hartley Act of 1947, and the McCarran Act of 1950.
The records of ACCESSION NO. 3120-002 primarily date from to 1960s and 1970s. Included are wage scale books from 1944, 1950, and 1952. This accession also includes job descriptions and postings, which help to detail the nature and division of labor at IWA lumber mills.
Open to all users, but access to portions of the papers restricted. Contact repository for details.
See also International Woodworkers of America Records, Acc. Nos. 4000-001 and 4000-002 in Special Collections.
Brophy, John.; Nelson, Pete.; Fadling, J. E.; Bordsen, Ed.; Dennee, John.; Hartung, A. F.; Winn, Carl.; Belka, Walter.; Winn, Ralph.; Taylor, E. W.; Larsen, Karly; International Woodworkers of America.Local 3-101 (Everett, Wash.)$vArchives; Progressive Party (U.S.: 1948); Weyerhaeuser Timber Company; Eclipse Lumber Company; International Woodworkers of America; International Woodworkers of America.$bNorthern Washington District Council. No. 2; International Woodworkers of America.$bWestern Washington District Council. No. 23; International Woodworkers of America.$bWestern States Regional Council. No. 3; Washington Industrial Union Council; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); International Woodworkers of America.$bInternational Negotiating Committee; Industrial Union Council (CIO). Snohomish County; International Woodworkers of America. Local 23-93 (Sultan, Wash.); International Woodworkers of America. Local 3-199 (Bellingham, Wash.); International Woodworkers of America. Local 23-46 (Bellingham, Wash.); International Woodworkers of America. Local 23-75 (Sedro Woolley, Wash.); International Woodworkers of America. Local 2-54 (Anacortes, Wash.); International Fishermen and Allied Workers of America. Cannery Workers. Local 18 (Everett, Wash.); United States.$bNational Labor Relations Board; United States.$bNational War Labor Board (1942-1945); United States.$bWest Coast Lumber Commission.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.).$bPolitical Action Committee; International Woodworkers of America.$bLocal 3-101 (Everett, Wash.).$bShop Stewards Council; International Woodworkers of America.$bLocal 3-101 (Everett, Wash.).$bExecutive Board; International Woodworkers of America.$bLocal 3-101 (Everett, Wash.).$bWood Products Safety Committee; International Woodworkers of America.$bLocal 3-101 (Everett, Wash.).$bPublishers Forest Products Company.$bAnacortes Branch; International Woodworkers of America.$bLocal 3-101 (Everett, Wash.).$bWeyerhauser Standing Committee; International Woodworkers of America$vArchives; Lumber and Sawmill Workers Union.$bLocal 2532 (Portland, Ore.); Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington)
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Logging; Washington (State)
- International Woodworkers of America Local 3-101 records, 1935-1979; 1937-1969; 3120-001; 10.51 cubic feet (21 boxes)
  The records of Local 3-101 date from the beginnings of the International Woodworkers of America (IWA) and document the early history of the Everett local and other locals in Western Washington which merged with 3-101. They document also the activities of the regional IWA organization which was the Northern Washington District Council No. 2 from 1937 until amalgamation with District 3 in 1953 produced the Western Washington District Council No. 23, followed by the Western States Regional Council in 1959. This accession also provides documentation of industrial unionism in Snohomish County from the beginnings of the CIO.
  The bulk of the papers date from the 1940s and 1950s, a time when unions, union leaders, and the CIO especially, were under attack. A common concern throughout the records is anti-labor legislation such as the Taft-Hartley Act of 1947, and legislation which was used against organized labor, such as the Smith Act and McCarran Act. The second "Red Scare" of this period not only led to attacks on the union from outside, but created or exacerbated disputes and divisions within both the IWA and CIO. The Woodworkers' history of local independence and rank and file control contributed to problems with their leadership and disputes between districts, hindering efforts toward industry-wide negotiations. Not until 1943 were negotiations industry-wide in both the fir and pine regions.
  RECORDS SUBGROUP I: INTERNATIONAL WOODWORKERS OF AMERICA, LOCAL 3-101 RECORDS. The bulk of correspondence in SERIES II: GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE is from 1948-1954 although there is little in 1952. Additional correspondence scattered throughout other series, such as MINUTES, NEGOTIATIONS, and CASE FILES, (SERIES III, IV, XII) of the Everett local are very incomplete; most of these remain in the custody of Local 3-101. There are no minutes from the Eclipse branch after 1945, none from the Weyerhaeuser mills, except the shop committees, and only fragments from the Granite Falls and Sultan branches. Minutes of the District Council Executive Board are nearly complete from 1949 to 1957.
  SERIES III: MINUTES, 1944-1957, contains minutes from the IWA Eclipse Mill, Granite Falls, and Sultan branches. It also includes meeting minutes of the executive councils for Northern Washington Districts 2, 3, and 23.
  SERIES IV: NEGOTIATIONS, 1940-1968, contains correspondence, minutes, proceedings chronologically and represent largely regional negotiations that included the Everett local. They have been separated into "General" and "IWA Western Washington Health and Welfare Committee and Employers' Health and Welfare Committee" subseries.
  The only strike that is well documented in SERIES VI: STRIKES, 1954 is the 1954 12 week, joint IWA - Lumber and Sawmill Workers (AFL) strike which shut down all major operations through the Douglas fir region. The records document the Everett local's part in the strike.
  SERIES VII: RESOLUTIONS,circa 1941-1955, contain resolutions from Local 101, the IWA District Council and the Snohomish Industrial Union Council on a variety of local and national issues.
  Many partial financial records have been retained, primarily to serve as membership lists. They primarily document the activity of Local 2-101 from 1941-1976 in SERIES X: FINANCIAL RECORDS.
  SERIES XIII: REPORTS includes much material which was generated by the District Council. The economic reports statistically describe the state of the lumber industry.
  SERIES XX: SUBJECT SERIES - Taft-Hartley, 1947- circa 1957, consists of CIO memos explaining the new law and also documents Local 101's compliance with Taft-Hartley requirements in 1949-1951.
  The Karly Larsen Defense Committee, 1953, was a "Committee of IWA Neighbors and Friends of Karly Larsen," the 1st Vice President of Western Washington District No.23 of the IWA. Larsen was being tried under the Smith Act, an alien registration act, and faced deportation.
  SERIES XXVIII: NELSON (PETE) COMMITTEE: 1949-1951, concerns the attempted deportation by the Immigration Service of the Business Agent of Local 2-101, Pete Nelson. Additional papers relating to these deportation cases are in RECORDS SUBGROUP 7: SNOHOMISH COUNTY INDUSTRIAL UNION COUNCIL.
  The records subgroups of IWA Locals 23-93, 23-46, 3-199, 23-75, 2-54 contain records of small locals which merged with Local 101 in the 1950's. RECORDS SUBGROUP 2; IWA Local 29-93 (Sultan), 1935-1957, contains the earliest records in the accession. Its SERIES III: MINUTES, begins with the formation of the union as Local 2614 of Sawmill and Timber Workers (AFL). It subsequently became IWA Local 23-93 in September 1937 and merged with 23-101 in 1957. The Sultan local included sub-locals in Skykomish, Granite Falls, Monroe, and Granite. 1957-1958 minutes from the Sultan Branch of 23-101 are filed in the main body of the accession. Locals 23-46 and 3-199 of Bellingham are not the same union. Their records are represented in RECORDS SUBGROUP 3 and RECORDS SUBGROUP 4 respectivly. 23-46 merged with 23-75 of Sedro-Woolley on October 1, 1955 and 23-75 merged with 3-101 on October 18, 1959. Local 3-199 of Bellingham, 1955-1971, was a boom men and rafter's union. Local 2-54 of Anacortes also merged with 3-101 in 1959. The records of some of these unions are represented in this collection. Specifically, RECORDS SUBGROUP 4: WOODWORKERS OF AMERICA, INTERNATIONAL. LOCAL 3-199 (Bellingham), RECORDS SUBGROUP 5: WOODWORKERS OF AMERICA, INTERNATIONAL. LOCAL 23-75 (Sedro Woolley), RECORDS SUBGROUP 6: WOODWORKERS OF AMERICA, INTERNATIONAL. LOCAL 2-54 (Anacortes)
  RECORDS SUBGROUP 7: SNOHOMISH COUNTY INDUSTRIAL UNION COUNCIL.(CIO), 1936-circa 1964, documents the political activities of that organization and its differences with the national CIO leadership. Its political activities included lobbying against anti-labor legislation in the state, support for Harry Bridges and the IWA leaders who were threatened with deportation. SERIES II: GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE in this subgroup includes resolutions from the CIO Executive Board on a variety of issues, including the purging of several left wing unions from the CIO.
  RECORDS SUBGROUP 8: FISHERMEN AND ALLIED WORKERS OF AMERICA, INTERNATIONAL. CANNERY WORKERS. LOCAL 18 (EVERETT), 1937-1942, is a sub-subgroup of the SIUC because the Cannery Workers, Local 18 was a member of that organization. The Cannery Workers organized as Local 18257 of the AFL on October 11, 1937, but switched affiliation and on November 22, 1937 received a CIO charter as Local 170. On May 23, 1938 the Cannery Workers voted to change affiliation again to the Fishermen and on August 1 received a charter as Cannery Workers, Local 18 of the United Fishermen Union of the Pacific (CIO). By January 1941 the Everett Cannery Workers Local 18 was affiliated with the International Fishermen and Allied Workers of America (CIO).
  Open to all users, but access to portions of the papers restricted. Contact repository for details.
  Ken Schott, IW of A Local 3-101, Everett, September 01, 1980
  - INTERNATIONAL WOODWORKERS OF AMERICA, LOCAL 3-101, 1940-1976; RECORDS SUBGROUP 1 (Box-folder 1/1-16/4)
    - ORGANIZATION, 1947-circa 1958; SERIES I (Box-folder 1/1-1/2)
      - Schedule, Rules, and By Laws., 1947-1956 (Box-folder 1/1)
      - Constitution-Proposed Revisions, 1951-circa 1958 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE -[Organized Chronologically], 1940-1976; SERIES II (Box-folder 1/3-2/16)
      - General Correspondence, 1940 (Box-folder 1/3)
      - General Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 1/4)
      - General Correspondence, 1943 (Box-folder 1/5)
      - General Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 1/6)
      - General Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 1/7)
      - General Correspondence, June 1948-May 10 1948 (Box-folder 1/8)
      - General Correspondence, June 10 1948-September 14 1948 (Box-folder 1/9)
      - General Correspondence, September 15 1948-October 6 1948 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - General Correspondence, October 7 1948-January 4 1949 (Box-folder 1/11)
      - General Correspondence, January 6 1949-January 28 1949 (Box-folder 1/12)
      - General Correspondence, February 1, 1949-March 3, 1949 (Box-folder 1/13)
      - General Correspondence, April 7 1949-June 29 1949 (Box-folder 1/14)
      - General Correspondence, July 1949-August. 31 1949 (Box-folder 1/15)
      - General Correspondence, September 1949 (Box-folder 1/16)
      - General Correspondence, October 1949-December 22 1949 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - General Correspondence, January 1950-May 30 1950 (Box-folder 1/18)
      - General Correspondence, June 1950 (Box-folder 1/19)
      - General Correspondence, July 5 1950-August 25 1950 (Box-folder 1/20)
      - General Correspondence, September 1950-October 1950 (Box-folder 1/21)
      - General Correspondence, November 1950-December 26 1950 (Box-folder 1/22)
      - General Correspondence, January 4 1951-February 28 1951 (Box-folder 1/23)
      - General Correspondence, March 1951-May 1951 (Box-folder 1/24)
      - General Correspondence, June 1951 (Box-folder 1/25)
      - General Correspondence, July 1951 (Box-folder 1/26)
      - General Correspondence, September 1951-October 1951 (Box-folder 1/27)
      - General Correspondence, August. 1951 (Box-folder 2/1)
      - General Correspondence, November 1951 (Box-folder 2/2)
      - General Correspondence, December 1951 (Box-folder 2/3)
      - General Correspondence, 1952 (Box-folder 2/4)
      - General Correspondence, January 1953-March 1953 (Box-folder 2/5)
      - General Correspondence, April 1953-May 1953 (Box-folder 2/6)
      - General Correspondence, June 1953-July 1953 (Box-folder 2/7)
      - General Correspondence, August 1953-September 1953 (Box-folder 2/8)
      - General Correspondence, October 2 1953-December 16 1953 (Box-folder 2/9)
      - General Correspondence, January 2 1954-February 25 1954 (Box-folder 2/10)
      - General Correspondence, March 1954-April 1954 (Box-folder 2/11)
      - General Correspondence, May 1954-August 1954 (Box-folder 2/12)
      - General Correspondence, September 1954-December 1954 (Box-folder 2/13)
      - General Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 2/14)
      - General Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 2/15)
      - General Correspondence, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 2/16)
    - MINUTES, 1944-1957; SERIES III (Box-folder 2/17-3/9)
      - Eclipse Mill Branch, 1944-1945; Subseries A (Box-folder 2/17)
      - Granite Falls Branch (SEE ALSO Box/Folders 16/7-17/11), 1957-1959; Subseries B (Box-folder 2/18)
      - Sultan Branch (SEE ALSO Box/Folders 16/7-17/11), 1957-1958; Subseries C (Box-folder 2/19)
      - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, 1945-1951; Subseries D (Box-folder 2/20-3/4)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 2/20)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, June-August 1949 (Box-folder 2/21)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, October-December 1949 (Box-folder 2/22)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, February-May 1950 (Box-folder 2/23)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, August-October 1950 (Box-folder 2/24)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, December 1950 (Box-folder 3/1)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, February-April 1950 (Box-folder 3/2)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, June-August 1951 (Box-folder 3/3)
        - Northern Washington District Council No. 2. Executive Board, October-December 1951 (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Washington District Councils Nos. 2 and 3. Joint Meeting. Executive Boards, June 1951; Subseries E (Box-folder 3/5)
      - Western Washington District Council No. 23. Executive Board., 1953-1957; Subseries F (Box-folder 3/6-3/9)
        - Western Washington District Council No. 23. Executive Board., February-August 1953 (Box-folder 3/6)
        - Western Washington District Council No. 23. Executive Board., October-December 1953 (Box-folder 3/7)
        - Western Washington District Council No. 23. Executive Board., 1955 (Box-folder 3/8)
        - Western Washington District Council No. 23. Executive Board., 1956-1957 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - NEGOTIATIONS, 1940-1968; SERIES IV (Box-folder 3/10-7/4)
      - Fir Case, 1943; Subseries A (Box-folder 3/14)
      - General-Chronologically Ordered, 1940-1968; Subseries B (Box-folder 3/10-13, 4/1-6/7, 7/1-4)
        - General, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 3/10)
        - General, January-February 1944 (Box-folder 3/12)
        - General, March 1944 (Box-folder 3/13)
        - General, April-November 1944 (Box-folder 4/1)
        - General, January-September 1945 (Box-folder 4/2)
        - General, October-December 1945 (Box-folder 4/3)
        - General, January 1946 (Box-folder 4/4)
        - General, February 1946 (Box-folder 4/5)
        - General, March 1946 (Box-folder 4/6)
        - General, April-June 1946 (Box-folder 4/7)
        - General, July-December 1946 (Box-folder 4/8)
        - General, January 1947 (Box-folder 4/9)
        - General, February 1946 (Box-folder 4/10)
        - General, May 1947 (Box-folder 4/11)
        - General, April 1947 (Box-folder 4/12)
        - General, May-December 1947 (Box-folder 4/13)
        - General, January 1948 (Box-folder 4/14)
        - General, February 1948 (Box-folder 4/15)
        - General, March 1948 (Box-folder 4/16)
        - General, May-December 1948 (Box-folder 5/1)
        - General, 1949 (Box-folder 5/2)
        - General, 1950 (Box-folder 5/3)
        - General, January 1951 (Box-folder 5/4)
        - General, June-August 1951 (Box-folder 5/5)
        - General, October-December 1951 (Box-folder 5/6)
        - General, January-February 1952 (Box-folder 5/7)
        - General, March-April 1952 (Box-folder 5/8)
        - General, May-June, December 1952 (Box-folder 5/9)
        - General, January 1953 (Box-folder 5/10)
        - General, February-March 1953 (Box-folder 5/11)
        - General, April-May 1953 (Box-folder 6/1)
        - General, June-August 1953 (Box-folder 6/2)
        - General, 1955 (Box-folder 6/7)
        - General, 1959 (Box-folder 7/1)
        - General, 1961 (Box-folder 7/2)
        - General, 1968 (Box-folder 7/3)
        - General, 1961 (Box-folder 7/4)
      - IWA Western Washington Health and Welfare Committee and Employers' Health and Welfare Committee, 1954, 1957; Subseries C (Box-folder 6/3-6, 8)
        - IWA Western Washington Health and Welfare Committee and Employers' Health and Welfare Committee, March 1954 (Box-folder 6/3)
        - IWA Western Washington Health and Welfare Committee and Employers' Health and Welfare Committee, March-April 1954 (Box-folder 6/4)
        - IWA Western Washington Health and Welfare Committee and Employers' Health and Welfare Committee, April-May 1954 (Box-folder 6/5)
        - IWA Western Washington Health and Welfare Committee and Employers' Health and Welfare Committee, May 1954 (Box-folder 6/6)
        - IWA Western Washington Health and Welfare Committee and Employers' Health and Welfare Committee, April-May 1957 (Box-folder 6/8)
    - STRIKES, 1950, 1952; SERIES V (Box-folder 7/5-7/6)
      - Assorted Financial Statements, Grocery Lists, Attendance Sheets, and Donation Lists, 1950 (Box-folder 7/5)
      - Correspondence and Report On Income and Expenditures for Dist. Strike and Lockout Fund, 1952 (Box-folder 7/6)
    - STRIKES, 1954; SERIES VI (Box-folder 7/7-8/4)
      - General Correspondence, 1954; Subseries A (Box-folder 7/7)
      - Minutes, 1954; Subseries B (Box-folder 7/7-7/10)
        - Minutes, June 1954 (Box-folder 7/8)
        - Minutes, July 1954 (Box-folder 7/9)
        - Minutes, July-September 1954 (Box-folder 7/10)
      - Membership, 1954; Subseries C (Box-folder 7/11-7/17)
        - Referral and Voucher Ledgers, 1954 (Box-folder 7/11)
        - Welfare, 1954 (Box-folder 7/12)
        - Welfare, 1954 (Box-folder 7/13)
        - Welfare, 1954 (Box-folder 7/14)
        - Welfare, 1954 (Box-folder 7/15)
        - Welfare, 1954 (Box-folder 7/16)
        - Welfare, 1954 (Box-folder 7/17)
      - Financial Records, 1954; Subseries D (Box-folder 8/1-8/2)
        - Financial Records, 1954 (Box-folder 8/1)
        - Financial Records, 1954 (Box-folder 8/2)
      - Financial Records, 1954; Subseries E (Box-folder 8/3-8/4)
        - Vouchers, 1954 (Box-folder 8/3)
        - Vouchers, 1954 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - ECLIPSE PLANT STRIKE, March 21-April 13 1957; SERIES VII (Box-folder 8/5)
    - STRIKES, 1961-1962; SERIES VIII (Box-folder 8/6-8/12)